[Music]
so what we're exploring in this film is
one of the different ways of knowing
that we've lost access to why are they
important and how do we bring them back
into the conversation so this will
include clips from Ian's McGilchrist
who's the author of the bestseller the
master his emissary and John Verve a key
we've had on the channel a few times as
well and who created the awakening from
the meaning crisis series we have a
brilliant systems theorist called Nora
Bateson and she's actually new to the
channel and then also Greg Thomas who's
also new to the channel who runs the
jazz leadership project and Bonita Roy
as well who's been on the channel a
couple of times who's also a brilliant
systems theorist and facilitator so
we're also launching this as a series
that I'm writing on medium and it's
going to be a little bit of a different
format than we've done before in that
it's a three article series and the
first article is launching at the same
time as this film so in addition to this
we've also recorded a conversation
between John Bob Athey and in
McGilchrist so then speaking for the
very first time which I actually
recorded yesterday probably put it out
in a week or two and it was really
interesting hearing them they really got
into a nice flow with each other and
felt that their ins perspective of the
left-brain right-brain
way of knowing and how our perception
itself is kind of split really mapped on
to John Vevey Keys really kind of
pioneering work with wisdom and in the
fourth generation cognitive science
space there's a lot of really
interesting parallels between them that
coming out even in the dialogues yeah
and the first article in this series
actually includes both genre Vicki Annie
McGill Chris works and compares and
contrasts them to see how do their
different models of how we perceive and
really the machinery of our perception
so are our brains and our entire bodies
and what is now called embodied
cognition how does that influence how we
perceive and what does it matter so
McGill Chris has his model of the the
bicameral mind so the way in which the
difference between our left and right
hemisphere has huge influence on how we
see the world and even in our culture
and then I had a conversation with John
Verve a key because I was curious about
this and knew that as a cognitive
scientist he would have a very
interesting take on it and
unsurprisingly he had a very interesting
take on it and he's actually been
working on what he calls the four
different ways of knowing so that became
a really really useful frame and I
wanted to just play a clip around that
so we can hear it from Dawn himself and
so as I've been researching it one of
the one of the core concepts that came
up was embodied cognition I don't know
that's definitely sounds like something
to talk to John for Vicki about though
here we are when we were setting this up
you mentioned that you're working on
something right now around four
different ways of knowing place to start
sure like you know it's in parts of the
series because one of the thesis of the
series is we've sort of lost touch and
this is picked up by the embodied
cognition approach we've lost touch with
sort of I don't mean you know you know
our sort of implicit lives but we've
lost theoretical touch an existential
touch with procedural knowing and
processional and propositional so let me
go through the four if you'll allow me
and I'm going to try I mean you know
taxonomy Zarn true or false
it's how consistent they are how good
they do at explication and explanation
and so and so forth so the one that
we're of course most familiar with when
we talk about no knowledge is knowing is
propositional knowing so this is the
kind of knowledge that you capture in
your beliefs about propositions like I
know that I know that the cat is a
mammal and so and we've done a lot of
work on that and we have this excellent
procedure for trying to improve our
propositional knowing it's called
science and or if you want to make it
more broadly science and history and so
I don't have too much to say about that
except that for various historical
reasons which I won't review right now
because I go over and then in detail in
the series that model of knowing has
come to predominate and if we've lost
the other kinds of knowing that had a
larger place for example in the ancient
and medieval worlds and in other
cultures too so procedural knowledge
procedural knowing I'll stick with
knowing because they want to emphasize
how much we're talking about the process
here and not the
okay so procedural knowing is knowing
how to do something knowing how to catch
a ball knowing how to ride a bike things
like that and it's captured not in
beliefs it's captured it in skills
that's procedural knowing respect
honorable knowing comes from the fact
that you're not just an intelligent
agent you're a conscious agent you have
consciousness and so this is the kind of
knowing you know by basically being able
to inhabit a perspective and what do I
mean by that well what I mean by that is
this is a way of knowing that is
relative to the state of mind you're in
so you know what it's like to be drunk
and how you and the world seem when
you're drunk you know what it's like to
be sober and then we can ask more
specifically well what is that knowing
like and so I try to articulate that
what it is is a phenomenon called
salience landscaping where the relevance
realization machinery is coming into our
online working memory and what we're
getting is a dynamic pattern of salience
what's standing out what's foreground
and background it the salting and
featuring how it's all so you know what
you're paying attention to what you're
ignoring that's your salience landscape
and so it gives you your your your
knowing of your here nowness so it gives
you your situational awareness so the
procedural skills ultimately sit in and
are nested by your prospective will
salience landscaping but then we have to
ask yeah but what what coordinates you
as an organism in the environment such
that a perspective is possible and so
that comes in and that's where we get
really deeply into the embodied
cognition also all all three of these
last three are deeply about embodiment
this is this is a participatory knowing
this is this is this is the way in which
you identify with and inhabit your mind
and body such that you right make
identities for the world
that are right karela v'n so you become
an agent in a world that is an arena to
you so for example your biology put
significant constraints
on how have you know sort of the
logistics of your cognition and it
limits how you can move around in the
world and then that means it puts
constraints on the kind of agency you
can exercise and it also puts
constraints on what aspects of the world
can be disclosed to you and in the
dialogue between Ian and John they
really covered new ground in terms of
their sort of models of the world John
the vaycay talks about fourth generation
cognitive science and our fourth
generation cognitive science is really
all about embodied cognition that this
whole sort of descartes ian split of the
mind and the body is gone in the latest
cognitive science that's that's no
longer a workable model which really
then brings it much more into kind of
Ian's realm because he is very scathing
about kind of how reductive we can be
and how reductive our models of
cognition can be so it's really
interesting seeing that John was able to
kind of explain and lay out - in a lot
of where the science is going which is
sort of this real excitement I think the
both of them
and that's something I think they both
share you know John rebecky talks about
that first for first of the four ways of
knowing is propositional knowing so
that's knowing that so propositional
knowing you know he describes it as
that's really we're quite good at that
that's the knowing of science and
history and we have methods for figuring
out what something is and knowing that
but we there's nothing wrong with that
of course but he points out that we have
over relied on it and that when we over
rely on it we start losing access to
these other ways of knowing which are
much more about being embedded and
participating in the world and having
sort of a deep kind of attunement with
the world around us and really similarly
Ian talks about how the the left
hemisphere which has come to dominate
much of our thinking is really narrowly
focused and it tends to break things
into their constituent parts so it's
it's it doesn't really see people as
people it sees them as kind of
assemblages of parts whereas the right
is much more designed for what we don't
know so approaching problems we don't
know and we talked on the channel a lot
about the importance of coming into this
liminal space something Jordan holders
talked about at length as well so
how do we come into this space where
we're not sure where we don't know and
we're comfortable being in there because
that way of knowing and that way of
perceiving allows us to solve problems
together that we can't if we come into
it thinking we know and also kind of
thinking the world is like a big
computer switchboard and if we just
tinker this and tinker that what we'll
kind of fix it that's a very I think Ian
would say that's a very left-brain way
of approaching problems and a
right-brain way of approaching problems
or let's say John might call it more and
more participatory knowing since we're
sort of having a back and forth with the
world and we're deeply engaged in it and
we can feel everything around us and
we're you know aware of what's salient
in our environment that that is more
similar to that right-brain way of
knowing and that's that is the one of
the main ways in which we perceive
that's really missing from a lot of the
cultural conversation so with all the
materialist reductionist kind of ethos
we live in and it's also missing very
often from systems change conversation
so through all these conversations I
became aware of sort of my own cognitive
bias which is that I'm I don't
necessarily see things as systems I'm
very focused in on the individual level
and kind of what does individual
transformation look like or what does it
look like where when we're in groups and
I realize there's kind of a piece
missing of my own thinking which was
while I'm interested in systems theory
how does this apply to systems theory
you know how do these different ways of
knowing influence how we look at very
very complex systems and the person I
found at talk Iran that was Nora Bateson
and Nora Bateson is well known this
whole systems change area and she runs
the Bateson Institute which is an
institute based in Sweden which looks to
expand the work of her father Gregory
Bateson Gregory Bateson is really well
known philosopher of the 20th century
and particularly well known for really
growing that whole field of complexity
and systems theory and also cybernetics
you know he coined a bunch of phrases
like a double bind for example so Nora's
been kind of carrying on that work and
doing a lot of research and one of the
things I find really interesting about
her perspective is that it's much more
of a right brain
kind of participatory take on the way
systems work so very often in the system
change space people use engineering
language so they kind of try and map out
a mental model that captured all of this
complexity and her take is that that
doesn't work because the systems
themselves are learning and these
systems especially living systems act
very differently to like a dead system
so the ecology of a forests or the
relationship you have with your family
or your workplace or whatever it might
be is a completely different thing than
an engine or a switchboard and yet very
often people use the language of
engineering to try and explain those
deep living systems so a whole different
language is needed and that's I think a
really key point which doesn't get
spoken about all that much is that our
language influences our way of knowing
and reinforces it so it's very important
to be thinking about ways of perceiving
like aesthetic knowing for example
there's the kind of feel of quality of
something you know how is that quality
but you can't quite put your finger on a
describe so that really ties in as well
to what in McGilchrist have talked about
and john drove a key it's this moving
beyond just that reductionist frame and
widening out and once we do that that's
again why I think these different ways
of knowing or in lost ways of knowing
because we have kind of lost access to a
lot of them are really really important
so let's play a clip from Nora talking a
little bit about her her take on the
kind of wider system space idea of
pulling things out of context to study
them measure them to find them was not
going to be a very useful contribution
to my understanding of how they are in
contexts multiple contexts across you
know suddenly the system's model went
from being an engineering map to being a
3d moving thing in time there's plenty
of great information you can get with
reductionist process but you can't
understand how the vitality of a living
system is actually shift
and moving and if it's not shifting and
moving it's not alive anymore so we have
a we have a conundrum there of how we're
going to think about what information is
when so much of what has been developed
in terms of what we think of as
authorized information aesthetic and
what we need to understand and respond
to is complex and alive
it's amazing we've got this far but
anyway there's been issues so warm data
is that warm data became the way that I
just started to describe how things are
happening through and across and within
multiple contexts simultaneously so Alli
you've been spending like over a month
researching this interviewing people
writing really long articles on medium
why why is this so important why do you
think this is so important why do you
think it's valuable to add to the
conversation so for me it's really
important because I think it's a missing
crucial missing piece of the
conversation that's potentially of
existential importance so there are a
lot of tribes online right now Peter
Lindbergh is called these mimetic tribes
and he's listed about 25 of them but
there's who knows how many more and what
I became really interested in is there
are a quite a high number of these
tribes whether we're talking about
queuing on
extinction rebellion deep adaptation
game be the list goes on and on who for
probably a really good reason are
focused on how do we save humanity in
some way or another how do we get
through the the crises we might be
facing and they're often in a kind of
narrative warfare
the reason it's frustrating is because
that I feel they're also relying on one
particular type of knowing and excluding
different types of knowing and that type
of knowing is what John Rivera calls
propositional knowing so it's knowing
that and we know that gold is a mineral
for example and knowing that is great
it's important that we know that we have
mental
but when we over rely on mental Maps we
create effectively ideological camps and
the more we rely on them and the more we
try and make our maps fit into the world
and almost kind of trying to make the
world order our Maps
rather than the other way around the
more we polarized into these tribes and
it just seems to me completely
counterintuitive and ineffective so what
I became really curious about was what
are the other ways of knowing not what
we know not what should we do or where
should we go or how do we fix this
problem but in what way should we start
perceiving in order to be able to see
and as Daniels macton Berger says make
sense sense make effectively so that we
can actually move forward and so that we
can come together effectively and
propositional knowing alone just
definitely won't cut it we need to have
a much more limited way of knowing we
need to be able to come out a problem
with the attitude of I don't know of
this uncertainty and from that
uncertainty also comes a certain comfort
with chaos and that's something I really
don't see a lot of in a lot of these
these groups is being comfortable with
chaos because chaos is really difficult
to describe and you have to I think and
this is what's really come out of
talking to all these people you have to
be in some kind of space of letting go
in order for that to work you have to be
willing to not know and you have to be
comfortable with just just how complex
systems are just how complex people are
you can't use game theory to solve
everything you know for example the
prisoner's dilemma breaks down pretty
rapidly if one of those prisoners is
having a deep religious awakening during
it you know this was part of over
rationalization which also happens what
in McGilchrist would refer to as kind of
a left brain dominant perspective so
that became a really interesting acquire
II for me what what are these different
ways of knowing how do we access them
where do they add value and crucially
how do we take them without throwing
away the propositional knowing so that
we are doing a yes and and we kind of
bring them together in a certain way
what's the what's the best way to bring
them together so Ian McGilchrist
famously wrote the book master and
emissary so Ian is a psychiatrist and
academic
and has a very broad perspective so what
master his emissary does is looks at
kind of a structure of the brain the
left brain versus the right brain and
those sort of different ways of
perceiving the world and then maps it on
to culture maps it on to history and
says that we are we have several times
in the past move from a more holistic
balanced perspective to a more left
brain atomistic reductive perspective
and when we do that we get ourselves
into trouble and that's probably
happening again now like we might have
time to avoid it but I know
Ian's perspective will play a very short
clip now what would be the elevator
pitch for mastering as emissary it's
that we are not aware that our reality
is constructed by two different systems
if you like we focus on different
aspects of reality and therefore
construe a world with different
qualities and the first part of the book
explains that in terms of
neuropsychiatry
philosophy and the second part of the
book suggests that in the history of the
West three times we have been in a
position where to begin with a
civilization flourished when it kept
both these visions together that of the
right hemisphere and that of the left
but then in every case and I believe
we're repeating the pattern for the
third time as the civilization
overreached itself and things
deteriorated and the mindset became more
rigid more bureaucratic less imaginative
less flexible less in touch with reality
and became locked into a way of thinking
which is that the left hemisphere which
is useful it's not a mistake that we
have it but it cannot be our way of
contacting reality a simple way of
putting it is it's like mistaking the
map for the territory yeah there was a
concept that John the vaycay and Ian
talked about in their dialogues that
really struck home in this as well about
how we perceive the world let's
about reciprocal narrowing and could
there be such a thing as reciprocal
opening and so it's kind of complex idea
I'll play a little clip from it
now I had a strong belief that it's not
that reality is made up by us but it's
not that reality just independently
exists from us we Midwife reality into
being our consciousness which is never
completely separate from the
consciousness of what we're looking at
brings out an aspect of something and so
we are actually not just passive
observers or recipients in the cosmos we
are actors in the cosmos in bringing the
cosmos into being I want to respond to
that very deeply first of all I agree I
think part of the straightjacket I try
to get out of the series it's the the
you know the Lockean empiricism that the
mind is tugging Arase
and the Rousseau Ian romanticism that
the world is applying a blank canvas
upon which we paint our subjectivity I
think those are both wrong and so that's
why I've coined this phrase transgenic
tivity about trying to break out of the
subjectivity objectivity a polarization
of our epistemology so I think that's a
deep mistake and so I think that noticed
that that idea so this will sound like a
slight digression but one of my friends
and colleagues Mark Lewis he's doing
some of the premiere work on addiction
right now and he's trying to replaces
the disease model of an addiction which
does not is not well supported by a lot
of data it's well funded by governments
but it's not well supported by data with
a learning model um and he calls it
reciprocal narrowing so it goes like
this let's say I get slightly drunk I
lose some cognitive flexibility and so I
can't notice as many options in the
world so the world starts to narrow a
bit
I then internalize this which then
narrows and you get this reciprocal
narrowing until you can't notice - any
alternatives and you can't notice any
way in which you could be other than you
are and then you're the addict you're
trapped right and I think that's all
right um I think that
I think it's a brilliant account of
addiction it supports much more of the
empirical data when I had life's with
Mark I said to him and that's why I
brought in the niels photonic tradition
I said but mark if there's reciprocal
narrowing there must be reciprocal
opening and he went you're right
and I said that you know and I think
this is you know the whole idea of the
Anna gaga that what we can do is we can
put ourselves into that and you called
it that openness in which right and I
think this is part of what what I see
god I sent stock was circling how he's
trying to enact hi to Gary
Heidegger as Alafaya right is this
reciprocal opening right and so it and
and and and then work by Erin and other
shows that's how you fall in love with
something like if you disclose something
and then I disclose and you do that
reciprocal opening where I open up what
I can be for you and that leads you to
open up what you can be for me and then
we reciprocally open we fall in love
with each other and so right and that
that I think that an agar get processed
right that reciprocal opening and you
can see it in flow States and like
that's that that that's one way of
trying to get this notion of noticing
and dialogue the biological relationship
into you know we can connect it with
practices the ring agent that's really
interesting you know because Joan is
increasingly interested in practices
like circling or even parkour where we
and of course he himself is an
experienced meditator and you know Tai
Chi practitioner what are those
practices that we can actually start
engaging in that create that opening as
opposed to the narrowing because it
almost feels like from these
conversations that the narrowing is is
almost our default that we have to
actively work to unlock you know we have
a left brain culture we have one that
high you know really focuses on
propositional knowing so to access those
different areas we need to start doing
something with it and so another person
I spoke to a few people around this
people who are actually doing something
in this space one of the most
interesting was at Greg Thomas so Greg
runs with his wife Jule something called
the jazz leadership project jazz is
really fascinating to me because jazz
has been used by a few people on the
channel
including Daniel attenberger Jordan Hall
and Jamie wheel in the making sense of
sense making film we put out as this
metaphor for collective intelligence
right so if the idea is we can't make
sense of the world anymore
well using the tools we used to use we
have to come together in some way and
make sense together
how does it actually look like what's
the best way for us to come into some
kind of coherence where we're really
listening to each other and something
new is emerging between us
as we talk and the metaphor they use in
that was jazz you know and it's not the
only people who've used that metaphor
and then I got really interested in what
like jazz is a really excellent metaphor
for that and Greg Thomas has not only
run the Jazz leadership project where
they're actually taking people into
transformation you know leadership
workshops you know even corporate change
workshops using jazz as a model but he's
also an integral theorist and really
interested in collective intelligence
really like knows a lot about the theory
of it so we had a really interesting
conversation with him around how this
metaphor of jazz can be used to
understand you know different ways of
knowing we have a concept called
ensemble mindset that uses the idea of
collective intelligence our brief
elevator description of Ensemble - it
would be collaborative co-creation
through collective intelligence so it
encompasses collaboration working
together co-creation when you say
co-creation then that means that there's
more than one and there is also an idea
that there's multiple going on but we're
doing it together and the collective
intelligence I think is very closely
tied to what creativity researcher and
jazz pianist Keith Sawyer called
group genius which takes the concept of
flow which his dissertation adviser
Mihai Csikszentmihalyi
of course famously wrote about and
extends it to groups working together
and we see that
hear it and feel it in jazz all the time
so what we've been doing through the
jazz leadership project is applying it
to personal and organizational
development through workshops with a
live jazz band if you're coming from two
completely different or disparate
perspectives you got to have some type
of common ground from which to then have
that conversation so in jazz that common
ground is usually knowledge of the Blues
there has to be a common ground of
shared values shared meaning so that's
your conversation in your interaction
can then really engage in that emergent
quality of something new and potentially
better coming out of it if you don't
have it
then there's got to be some grounding
for the conversation in the first place
and of course we see this in politics
where the the different camps that are
available because of the camps they're
in often times these days they don't
even have the willingness to engage in
conversation and I mean conversation not
where they're just arguing back and
forth I mean where they're truly
listening so that goes back to listening
and jazz leaves your project we have
three levels of listening that I'd like
to share with you
the first is just being attentive you
know really focusing on what the other
person is saying
then there's empathetic listening where
you include an open heart and you can
feel or you you listen deeply to feel
where the other person is coming from
and then there's generative listening
which we get from auto schirmer's theory
you concept where a generative listening
is open heart and open will so you link
to one another and then you are feeling
one another kind of like whole body like
this cognitive heart gut the whole thing
and then you're working together to
co-create a future future possibilities
are there so greg has that's really cool
of how we come together and work
together and create something new and
another person is doing that is Bonita
Roy who we found on the channel a few
times is also a systems theorist and a
facilitator who runs what she calls
collective insight practice a lot of
parallels with with what happens in say
a jazz ensemble etc it's coming together
it's a little bit different that's
coming together to specifically rather
than play music come to a collective
insight and but need to had a really
interesting kind of watch out for this
space you know I'm it's a cognitive trap
I found myself coming into which is if
we go
okay there's too much propositional
rigid model-making going on and there's
too many people who are using
engineering language trying to explain
something that's very complex the swing
that can happen is well that means the
embodied really flowing intuitive people
are better in some way and of course
that's not the case it's it's always
both are needed so when you're doing
collective insight practice actually
people are processing something but one
comes down abstract that's the social
processing temperament and one comes out
as narrative
why you always like this and there's a
tendency see that think that what is
more important than the other they're
both triggered they're both out of
regular that their ethics are not
regulated now but we tend to think the
narrative mythic is somehow closer to
anchored and body it's just a different
social processing energy you have to
process that energy and social space is
going to come out whether narrative or
abstract i bonita points out that when
when people come together to do
collective insight practice that is the
main fault line that cups up there's
people who explain the world through
stories and there's people who explain
the world through mental models and very
often they sort of clash but it's very
important that we find a way to whatever
side we're on understand that that's
just another way that that person has of
seeing the world and explaining their
experience and I think there's another
parallel that I pick up a lot in some
more alternative circles there's a real
a version to the former like
propositional ways of knowing and that I
think if like that is really really
important like stories
so we learnt we've both trained as
counselors and the idea in counseling is
that you are you're talking your way to
more insight you're talking your way to
understanding yourself better but that
can be like so many of those kind of
therapeutic models I think both of us
were to read don't actually work that
well if they're not including the wisdom
of the body if they're not including
like what are you feeling in this moment
what and some kind of potentially
emotional clearing work as well of like
maybe sometimes you just need to go out
and shout and scream and get into the
like let that out it's not just about
talking your way to a solution but on
the other side you can also find in the
more alternative world an overemphasis
on the body and a complete denial of the
need for kind of processing story and I
think that the that for me is really
interesting that and my sense is having
having kind of gone into this work and
trained in this work is that both are
needed that we need to do the sort of
clearing the the embodied work and kind
of be really alive to what's coming up
in our bodies but also we do need to
articulate it it's not one or the other
and so many times like I've been in a
breath workshop or I've been in some
kind of transformational workshop and
they're like okay let go of the story
let go the story and there's no space
given to talk about what might have come
up and my sense is that if we don't do
that then we don't articulate we don't
make real in our systems the insights
that we might have experienced in a more
liminal transformational space that
actually by articulating it like if you
have a transformative experience or you
have some kind of insight you actually
need to talk about it you need to make
it concrete by talking about you make
something that's kind of half understood
or half perceived real like there is
some deep in the beginning was the word
like there's a reason why that is at the
center of so much of our kind of
mythology is because by articulating by
conceptualizing we do make make things
more real and those two ways of knowing
have to be yea integrated in more of
these conversations
it's really interesting as you're
talking about that I'm kind of getting
an insight that I hadn't felt it before
so John DeBakey when we spoke he he
reference at one point that narrative
links the different ways of knowing
together so it links your propositional
knowing with the other types of knowing
it's kind of like a through line that
connects it all together and what it
feels like is that it's it's also
important to acknowledge that the
different ways of knowing are not always
appropriate for every situation like you
can't really walk around without any
narrative all the time like you might
have you know like in a meditation space
you you need some kind of narrative to
link your life together but there are
times where VirB a key points out that
narrative itself can become constraining
you know and that's like you said the
narrative the story we tell about
ourselves can start trapping us and
start blinding us to certain things so
while it's important it's almost feels
like it needs to be regenerated through
these other ways of knowing so by going
into a flow state for example the
reveille key points out that that kind
of propositional knowing and that
narrative ego goes into the background
and these other ways of knowing coming
to the foreground it's like you're
deeply present with whatever is going on
everything matters a lot you're really
there and that's really important it
feels like it kind of regenerates and it
gives us a little bit of space away from
the story and then when we go back to it
back to our ideas back to our things we
think we know we can kind of regenerate
them from that space so so it feels
important to kind of add that in that
it's not that we are looking to live
permanently in some different way of
knowing it's that there's kind of a
dance that has to take place between all
of these different types and we have to
use them in the right way at the right
time and he was also important to talk
about that John the Reiki in particular
his next focus is going to be on kind of
into subjective ways of knowing like
this put more participate or II way of
knowing and though he's got a series
coming up about Socrates called after
Socrates about the history of dialectic
and how we come to truth together how we
come to understanding together so I know
that this is sort of become a real focus
of his journey so it feels like a lot of
people are kind of aligning in this
space and just because I know that
there's more articles coming up
you want to talk about who you're going
to be who we're gonna be hearing from in
the other articles that you're gonna be
bringing out yeah so the series is in
three parts and as well as the people
we've mentioned we also have coming up
Jamie wheel and that kind of very
interesting perspective around utopia
dystopian thinking and how that's
feeding into this whole space then we
also have dr. Rosalind Watts who is a
psychedelic researcher so it's looking
at when we really go into the very
different space a very different state
what kind of information do we then get
access to and and why is that relevant
to the therapy why is it relevant to the
culture as well we have a few
facilitators and practitioners as well
who will be new names to a lot of people
but they're really doing a lot of
interesting work and we'll also be
drawing on peter Lindbergh's ideas as
well to kind of to keep a kind of map of
the mimetic tribes that are at play
right now in our world and what what
what missing what ways of knowing are
they currently missing and what might
help the conversation what might help
mediate between them let's say so we'll
put a link to the first article in the
series in the show notes and follow us a
medium if you'd like to see the other
team in the series and beyond that we're
also going to be putting more energy and
focus into our written output so we'll
be having more articles coming off a
medium in the future well done for
making it to the end I just wanted to
let you know a few things we've got
coming up including the biggest event
we've ever done the rebel wisdom
festival which will be a mix of ideas
and dialogues between people like Daniel
schmeckt and Berger Rupert Sheldrake
Jamba Vicki and many more and because
wisdom isn't just intellectual it's also
about practice will be offering
experiences like circling different
interpersonal dialogue mindfulness
breathwork
and many other with world-class
facilitators we're also running our
first online course called sense making
101 and if you're enjoying the content
you can help us make more by joining the
rebel wisdom club which will give you
discounts on the courses and the events
and also access to a load more content
on the website including all of our live
events it'll also give you access to our
growing community which is something we
want to make a real focus for 2020
adding more meetups and other services
from
embers so hope you enjoyed the film and
see you soon
you